thank you for tuning in
and i'll um i'm gonna set some context
in a moment
for my uh ongoing um
dialogue and uh reading
and reflecting on heidegger's on the way
to language which is a
conversation between heidegger and a
japanese philosopher
that we're reading together i think this
is the third or fourth video that we've
done so far
but first some housekeeping okay so
uh regarding upcoming things with
circling in the circling institute
uh we have i'm doing a demo
uh on
saturday the 31st
of october at 10 a.m
10 to 11 30 on pacific standard time
and it's a it's
if you're interested in looking at um
uh seeing a circle happen that i'll be
leading
i'll be there and while i'm leading it
um i'll have other co-leaders
who will be answering questions in the
chat
um and then when we're done when we're
done with this circle then
we'll open it up to questions of
discussion about it
so if you're interested in looking at
and seeing what um a a circle
circling is uh and you're new to it and
you want it and you have questions about
i want to see it and experience it a bit
um that will be then uh i'll put a link
to everything in the in the space below
um you know and on some level i'm always
circling on some level so even when i'm
all the videos that i do on the channel
i'm sure
you know you could probably implicitly
see circling all over the place
um however this will be an explicit
circle right so we'll be able to discuss
it and
geek out about it and talk about it so
the other thing is every thursday night
uh six
to six to nine pm on zoom we also have a
three hour
drop-in uh circling event
and i think we have a weekend coming up
in uh about a month from now
and we're opening for registration for
the next art of circling
uh this last one that um basically
got overfull so so
uh the demand and the ability to
supply uh to the demand
now that we're online and
um is is is rapidly becoming an equal
so if you're interested in art of
circling i recommend definitely
registering sooner than later
if you're interested in working with me
one-on-one
my emails below email me and let me know
that you're interested and then i'll
i'll talk with you about okay i it
that's all the housekeeping
so this was an awesome conversation with
chris
um this was a this gets into the part of
the dialogue that's
really it taught
it's the exact it's that example of like
a
having a stretch super super deeply
um with the mind
also with the soul uh
to start to cease see things that are um
not immediately intelligible um
this is a great example of this dialogue
really kind of i think
um how dear logos and philosophical
intimacy
right really uh
aspires towards the um unsayable
and it requires a certain kind of
respect and a certain
development uh stance an attitude
that one has with one's whole being and
so this
i think i think this is uh this is a
real
a real good example of that um in this
dialogue that we're reading with
with heidegger and the japanese
philosopher and also you'll hear the
backdrop of
um some some conversations that we will
be having coming up and that i have been
having like with daniel
about about the notion of emptiness and
sunyata
and how all that fits together
amongst all this so thank you for tuning
in um
uh feel free to feel free to
to pass this along to your friends and
uh
uh hit subscribe if you want to get
notifications for upcoming videos which
there
there's a bunch of them in the in
in in the pipeline all right
thank you so much
welcome my friend
thank you very much yes we try
we often do this we we plan on
we plan on you know reading and then we
get to talking and three hours later you
know
we just don't have any energy at the end
of it to keep reading
yeah whoever watches these has to have a
great deal of patience
and a sense of humor yeah
for all of our detours absolutely okay
so we're on page 24.
i'll go ahead and just start from the
first j so
i guess i'm today i'm the japanese
person and you're you're heidegger
yep okay and um
i'll just start reading and we can you
can listen to the last video to kind of
catch up if you want
all right from a great
distance i sense a kinship
between our word that is now
before my mind and your phrase
the phrase gives a hint of the nature of
language
it seems to me you have just said
a freeing word then that hint
would be the words basic character
only now that you speak of hint
a word i could not find something
becoming becomes clear to me that i had
merely
surmised when i read your letter on
humanism
and translated into japanese your
lecture on the
on holdren's eulogy homecoming
during the same period i was translating
christ
the silea
the nature of the german language must
be at the at must
sorry the nature of the german language
must at that time have come over you
like a waterfall
it did indeed and while i was
translating
i often felt as though i were wandering
back and forth between
two different language realities such
that at moments
irradiance shown on me which let me
let me sense that the wellspring
of reality from which those two
fundamental different languages
arise was the same
that's a it's what i at least pause and
silence to give
homage to what i think that i just heard
because i don't it's my understanding
you almost
can't get much more different than
japanese and german from my
understanding
like uhana arnot
i think she wrote uh the book on the
nature of the mind or something like
that and she
she said that she doesn't think actually
that
that that you could
the japanese language i think
asian language she's she couldn't see
how it could
ever actually have
um of
like got into physics or or
science these deep kind of like uh
these deep logical kind of
entities that will never have any
sensuous appearance at all
right because she says that the that
language is so
context oriented my senses is it and i
you know i don't know what but my sense
is it it banks on so much context that
just
it's the minimal amount of sound to
reveal the background
kind of implicit context where german is
very apparently very in almost a simple
way very structured so it
the exact thing happens right and so
so to hear that you know just to look at
the difference between the two
and just to hear him say that he sensed
what that they came from the same
spring wellspring it's just interesting
it's a much more much given what you've
just said um it's a much more meaningful
observation that it might seem at first
glance
given the two languages that are
actually encountering one another
totally yeah
you did not then seek for a general
concept
under which both the european and the
east asian languages could be subsumed
absolutely not when you now speak of
hints this freeing word
emboldens me to name to you the word by
which
to us the nature of language is how
shall we say
perhaps hinted
that is to the point
but even so i fear that to call your
your quote house of being unquote
a hint might tempt you and me
to elaborate the notion of hinting
into a guiding concept in which
we then bundle up everything
that must not happen all right
so i just want to i want to pause there
for a second and just touch on something
so in
in my conversation earlier today with
with daniel he was talking about
in in in german um
you know where heidegger talks a lot
about
thinking and being being something like
the same
right and he says that you know in
in english that
thinking is usually caught up with
concept the notion of concept which
means to grasp
right to grasp so
i think what what he's pointing to is
this
we got to be careful not to
conceptualize it into grasp
but there's a um in in the dialogue and
this is what
i think dialocus can do is is it can let
appear it can
it can let what we cannot grasp
gather into presence right and that if
we grasp it too much
right um we
uh we literally ch we conceal something
something like that right it's so it's
like a yeah it's like a it's like a
training in the optimal gripping
yeah of letting letting sorry having
just the kind of grip
that can keep that can keep the
emergence gathered and coherent
but that it does not grip so tightly as
to
um to sort of circumscribe
the the ambit or the potential of what
is being revealed
yeah so that it allows it to still be
open-ended yes so like even with the
sense of hint
right on some level just that word hint
is a way of
basically the optimal grip without too
tight but then he's warning
well we could easily just make that a
concept
that's right it the the light touch
can become the heavy touch if we're not
careful
that's right yeah that's right that's
right and so then the the
the the finesse of the use of language
is precisely the
technology by which we finish the grip
and so it's the care in its use is then
paramount and they're
cautioning one another in this instance
not to overuse it in such a way that it
constrains the life of that which it's
actually attempting to reveal
yes us and all of our positing
right that's right
self-positing all right
how will you prevent it
it can never be prevented in the sense
of being totally excluded
why not because the mode of conceptual
representation
insinuates itself all too easily into
every kind of human experience
even where thinking is in a certain
sense
conceptless even there
you need only recall how instantly you
accepted cookie's aesthetic
interpretation of iki
as appropriate even though it rests on
european that is to stay on metaphysical
ideas if i
understand you rightly you mean to say
that the metaphysical manner of forming
ideas
is in a certain respect unavoidable
that is what kant saw clearly in his own
way
yet we realize only rarely
the full implications of his
insight because kant was unable to
develop it beyond
metaphysics the unbroken rule of
metaphysics establishes itself even
where we do not expect it in the
elaboration of
logic into logistics oh
logic to logistics interesting
right which is i think something like
the elaboration
into id of ideation into act
yeah right that the that the
metaphysical
the the metaphysical circumscriptions of
kant
translate themselves into a certain form
of circumscribed logistics insofar as
the
the carrying out of being is concerned
i think that's part of what's meant by
this right
and this remember is on the heels of him
saying
this common wellspring between the two
legs
and so here we can start to see
this kind of i can i can hear socrates
in the background here
right of going well
let's show exactly how impossible
that thing you experienced was right
something like that i i
feel like uh yeah well something a
dialectic happening here with this
yeah socrates loves closed doors so that
he can open them right
yes do you consider
do you do you consider that a
metaphysical process
indeed i do and the attack upon the
nature of language which is concealed in
that
process perhaps the last attack from
that quarter remains
unheeded we must guard
all the more carefully the ways toward
the nature or reality of language
it would be enough if we were to succeed
only in building a bypass
between those ways
your speaking of hints seems to me to
indicate a trail
that might lead to such a path
but even to talk of a hint is to venture
too much
we understand only too well
that a thinker would prefer to hold back
the word
that is to be said not in order to keep
it
for himself but to bear it toward
his encounter with what is
to be thought i want to read that again
[Laughter]
i had this experience of like i ended up
reading myself down to my toenails and
it didn't pop up yet
again
[Laughter]
only too well that a thinker would
prefer to hold back the word that is to
be said
hold back the word is to be said not in
order to
keep it for himself not not to grasp it
but to bear it toward his encounter
with what is to be
thought wow so you know what comes to
mind you know what comes to mind to me
when you read this
that that that um that line
is so let's let's
socialize the concept for a minute with
a social example yeah
you know when you're you're with someone
and you know that in the offing
of the relationship or in the offing of
the conversation there is the presence
of an unspoken
maybe it's an unspoken topic or an
unspoken proposal
that must be broached it must be
broached because it remains
pregnant within the context of the
relationship but it hasn't yet been
brought to the center of its attention
yeah and
you know you know that
for the fullness of that relationship
and then
in virtue of that the the
the for the good of you and for the good
of this other person
that proposal whatever is in the offing
of that relationship
must surface but you also know you have
this
this um this is this apprehension
that if it surfaces too early it'll
become
ingrown right if it surfaces in the
wrong way right like that's something
very genuinely to worry about if it
surfaces too prematurely if it's spoken
in the wrong way at the wrong time in
the wrong context
it will die yeah
and and you know that
you know or or it'll become subject to
like a performative contradiction
where the thing that is said is not the
thing that is meant and lived
and so then the living and the acting
become
unjustly tethered to the spokenness of a
thing
when that thing is not what was meant to
be spoken
yes this happens all the time especially
in very very intimate relationships so
you have to find a way to surface the
proposal
whatever it is that is to be thought
jointly you have to surface it in such a
way you have to carry it in your
bearing more than the in explicit
contents of
your conversation because if you carry
it in your bearing
yes and it exists as an ins it
and it exists as the hint right that
he's talking about
yeah you will carry it to its natural
point of emergence
that's kairos right but if you try and
speak it ahead of its proper thought
the thought will be malformed right it
won't translate so that in order to
translate
that which is to be spoken you have to
carry it
unspoken until the point where it's
until the point where the appropriate
context for its spokenness
presents right and i think that's part
of what he's he's referring to here
right let's not like let's not have a
stillborn
baby in other words right right
let's be good midwives yeah well
exactly let's be good midwives and part
of being a good midwife
is forbearance yes right knowing to
wait right is knowing to wait
right i'm thinking of the term it gives
kind of more voluptuous to the term
withholding
like like to be with
right the holding of the articulation of
the thought
right like you're with it it's it is
intimate
it's not keeping secret
in fact it's maybe this is one of the
things
this is like this is the difference
between like a dumb silence
and a wise silence yes
right like a wise person being silent
and somebody who just doesn't know what
to say right
like there's a fullness to the silence
also it also strikes me
i really think about it but i noticed i
noticed with teaching
as it as a in the last number of years
well i bet you if i watched myself
and you played when i like in teaching
as i go back into my history i think i
probably you you watch me talk more and
more and more and more as you go back in
time
unless as you come forward in time
i think that's definitely
yeah it is it you're right it you know
it is
it's like it's
it is more about withholding
right the articulation of that thought
and and yeah it's very body it's very
bodily yes
very yes embodied
that's right that's right that's right
and so the withholding can be an act of
supreme
love oh yeah oh yeah right
totally and it and it reminds me
actually john and i were talking
yesterday about
um about about honesty
and how sometimes people use honesty to
be an implement
you know they brandish at people and
and then defend defend their
you know defend defend their sort of
obtrusiveness
their obtuse rather by by by saying well
you know i was just
being honest but the fuller virtue
the fuller virtue of honesty contains
within it
the the intuition of that forbearance
the intuition of that withholding
as you say because we think of
withholding truth
as being um as being a a
a disingenuous behavior but the
withholding of truth can simply mean to
bear the truth
unto its proper destination
right yes
and and it also admits
that part like you could say the truth
is distributed
it's shared by time right it's shared by
a temporality
it's shared by it's not like i possess
it
right it presupposes
no it i don't own it oh
yeah yeah that what a great point yes
it's like distributed across and it's
distributed within the listener
right it's distributed
in in the not sharing of the thought
yet it other things are determining what
it is
right you're yeah it's very interesting
i'm also that's a great point that
you're sharing in it you're partaking of
it but it's not a possession of yours
and so that also
tutors that sense of forbearance if you
don't think of it as something that is
incumbent upon you and then a sense of
ownership
then your your deference right
your deference to the natural time of
that truth will be
will be much more attentive
i'm wondering if this is maybe
a place where logos and emptiness
keep going well so logo speech
right one way of like especially
aristotle
basically almost well i mean
people are still figuring out what
aristotle said right but
but he really emphasized the speech of
logos right as discourse
as the act of speaking um
and if the thought right
is not to be said but withheld so i'll
read this again
to understand only too well a thinker
would prefer to hold back the word that
is to be said
to hold back the word that is to be said
right so withholding in some sense the
speech
right like we say logos they hold back
the logos
to be said in order not to keep it
for himself but to bear it
towards its encounter which is to be
thought is there an emptying going on
here
like is there some kind of sense in
which like
to bear the thought right without
speaking it
not to possess it right but
but to bear it toward
right i'm just i'm sensing some kind of
like there's almost like the
you're empty there's some kind of
emptying or there's some relationship to
emptiness or to
nothing or to absence here
that seems very connected to logos in
some way and i was wondering if that
it's a place it's a place that they both
meet
as you say zenyatta the native he said
native ground of logos
that's right sound of logos that's right
yeah the native sound of logos yeah yeah
emptiness
yeah because there's a
because what i'm hearing here is is
basically like so they talk about hint
a hint points to it's like points to
something but it doesn't
it doesn't uh it doesn't propose it's
not a proposition
right but then then they're warning
about and then they keep warning about
well
we got to be careful about this hint
because this hint will become
something right now we're talking about
actually there's a great danger here
to even almost anything right
there's a there's kind of a it is a
strange emptying out
of presencing through emptiness
in some way
so do you think that one of the things
that dialogues does
is to interfuse
speech with
with emptiness so that it becomes
ok so that it becomes a bearing
of the logos
it's i almost i mean even though it's
completely
it's completely against the spirit of
the way that we usually do things i'm
almost tempted to just
as a just as an exercise to think of it
almost in a formulaic way
that take the take the speech you know
take a little bit of that a little bit
of this mix it together
take the speech of you know take the
spokenness of the
of the of the the normal dialogue
suffuse it consciently
with emptiness with absence
right yeah and then then only then
does it become a carrier for logos
especially when it goes from
dialectic to dialogues
when it catches i think what so i was
so there's that quality of like where if
we go back uh just a couple of pages
here here's this
this one this one thing i've just read 8
000 times in my life because it's so
rich
um right
we japanese okay this is what we
japanese do not think it's strange if a
dialogue leaves undefined
right so the dialogue can leave
undefined
right it can it
it's it's talos right could
it could go on in the dialogue right
it's not strange to leave it
empty in a certain sense right um
undefined what is really intended or
even restore it back to the keeping of
the undefinable
so to me that's that starts to get at
this sense of sanyata like
uh as nishitani would talk about the
home ground
right of of beings is this kind of
absolute emptiness right
and that and that the beat like the
my sense is it is it it's what it's what
allows the logos
right to come into being
because whatever whatever the form and
function
of that which is um
it's like that in the he uses metaphor
in religion and nothingness a lot of
like how the fire
right can it burns and combusts and all
these things that you can describe
but it precisely doesn't burn itself
and it's precisely because it doesn't
burn itself is what it allows it to be
exactly what it is
and that he's saying that he's saying
that in that
sense the most primary what what's it
what it allows it what what a lot like
it's its emptiness is its own home
ground itself negation
in
so it's not like um it's not like an
emptiness that
it's kind of like if i move here's the
space without my hand
and then i move my hand in that space i
think we normally think about it like
well
occupied space you're filling it yeah
that's right that's right
but doesn't it what happens to the space
that's occupied
right if it wasn't there
then it couldn't have the hand right
there's something going on where the
space doesn't disappear for stuff to
happen
right this the space is within it's so
saturated with everything yet
because it's absolute it um
because it's absolute it it it is its
own
self negation and that's how it is it's
precisely the thing that self negates
and everything
right that's what makes it absolute so
it kind of just a little background
because i've been wrestling with this
the last number of weeks of
emptying this thing man do i feel like a
yankee
right trying to think about nothing
jesus christ it's like
i just keep going i keep finding myself
reunifying it
as a something that isn't something
that it's it's so habitual like we're my
i'm such a cartesian american all the
way through
they all are maybe if y'all are looking
at how to sell it
right what kind of profit you can make
from it
location location location yeah
emptiness well one of the other things
about this emptiness is one of the
things i've noticed in
in and kind of reading
reading ishitani here is
because he's he's actually doing
something that i don't think can happen
if you just start to read zen as a
westerner right
because what a lot of honestly what a
lot of um
eastern based practices that are
happening in america with the with the
with the people i see
is that they um they're coming from such
different as you're talking about here
such different
ontological or metaphysical grounds
that what ends up happening is things
like this
like and meditation ends up in something
like
they like the english speaker will
will assume a cartesian self
right will posit it to then
let it go
but that but the the the sense of what
itself is even what a mind is is
so fundamentally different on the east
that i don't think it ends up actually
being the same thing
so one of the things i'm finding with
which is great about nishitani
is he's going all the way he's going
deeply into the
this like the guts of the metaphysics
of aristotle and the the notion of
substance with being
right and going into dialectic right
between the two and starting to tease
out a way that a west
like the westerner can get a glimpse of
it and my experience of it so far
is it's a glimpse that's really
different than it's really a different
kind of glimpse it's like this
i guess it's similar to a coan right
and that you don't figure something out
like it's more like
you you're here listening to him you're
listening to him at some point all of a
sudden
your perception shifts right like oh
it's like this whole thing this is this
the emptiness is the one thing that's
not
occurring but yet it's floating within
everything and you
get this experience of it so
so there's a kind of like it does seem
like something like
the spontaneity of the dia logos and the
luminosity of when
the fire the logos catches that
that that there's something about that
that you lose track that you're even in
a dialogue
that that that it disappears seems to be
saturates the whole conversation and is
is very connected to it as well that
quality of
when the fire of the logos catches right
we're all
tripping out about about this this thing
the thing that's like
allowing for all of it is precisely that
we're not self-conscious
right that we've lost consciousness
around it right
so there's something about this where it
almost seems like heidegger's
in some way
in some way he's almost minding
he's almost minding to it catching he's
minding to like
no it's not it's not it's gonna light
when it lights right
he's a lot he's he's tending to the fire
it's not lit yet
and he's aware that he can't light it
right
something like that i i'm seeing time in
here timing
pregnancy withholding
yeah and he also seems to be doing the
very thing that he's like the very thing
that he's describing
you know bearing forth the hint but
letting it be unspoken
and waiting for as you say waiting for
the fire to catch waiting for the fume
terrarify
right waiting for the speech to
translate itself
into the logos by ultimately
being you know vanquished altogether
it's something that he's carrying forth
in the way that he's speaking about it
and so he's trying to i think simulate
the translation between the act and the
ideation in the exactly the way that
he's describing it
yeah right it's like i mean the metaphor
that we've used so often
that you i mean you you when you were
talking about nishitani's
talking about the fact that the fire the
fire cannot burn itself
out eckhart has a very similar
very very similar use of that same motif
um and no wonder no wonder but
so the dialectic if i'm getting you
right the dialectic
the dialectic between the speech
and the no thingness and the dialogue
those ultimately are the sticks that are
going to be rubbed together
that actually create the dialogues
right it's that's that's the dialectic
interaction
between the between between what is said
and the shunyata
whose space
backgrounds it yeah i i
see it almost as a foreground and a
background and it's the dialectic
the dimensional dialectic between the
foreground
and the background of those
those right those axes
right of the being in relation to the
dialogue
that end up sparking oh
totally and that isn't that isn't that
so much often the case
where what's in the background
right is arising out of the background
that's in the background and then
at some point you realize
that the foreground is
the background and you it catches and
then they interpenetrate each other and
that's where the fire
catches it's that's right right
that's right that's right okay so and
then let's take this foreground
and this foreground background way of
framing their interaction
place it in the context of an image
right so let's say what about the
in the image the imagistic dialogue or
the imaginal dialogue which is something
that i've been consumed with lately
right that what the dialogue with image
does is it creates dialogue between its
backgrounded and foregrounded contents
and constituents
and what that does is it actually
generates the depth of the image
that constitutes the world of the image
that becomes
absorbed and absorbing into the stream
of consciousness
right and so the interaction between
those axes is actually what
what well as you say you you for you
such it's
becomes such that you forget that you're
in it yeah
because suddenly right because it's
it's composure is your composure its
complexion is your complexion exactly
and you are inseparable from it right
right it's like it's like this zenyatta
is like the silent partner
yeah right it's like the silent word
next to every word it's like the
something like that right it's the act
of allowing or something
um yeah it
the the oh i just hit
what was it what was it i just had it
it's gone it's the it's the thing i just
got into
gone
[Laughter]
i knew i knew it i knew it and you're
not saying it yes i'm
i'm i'm um i'm holding back the word not
to keep it right
exactly exactly bear it towards
towards what i'm encountering it's
not your your uh
you're forgetting it is actually not an
act of forgetfulness it's an act of
deeper memory
yes exactly yes it's
neopost forgetfulness
all right i think we go
oh yeah i'm jason you go next straight
after so that is
yes uh
uh that is so is that it that's right it
went back
so we're here here i'll just start here
um
jay why did you do why did you take that
line again the line that we stopped and
pondered on for as long as we did why
don't you say it again and then we'll
just continue
okay cool we understand
only too well that a thinker would
prefer to hold back
the word that is to be said not in order
to keep
it for himself but to bear it towards
his
his encounter with what is to be thought
that isn't keeping with the hints they
are enigmatic
they beckon to us they beckon away they
begin us
toward that from which they unexpectedly
bear themselves toward
us
i'm going to read that one again they
beckon us toward that
from which they unexpectedly bear
themselves toward us so they've got the
by the bi-directionality the coming the
coming toward is also the coming back
yeah which is kind of yeah it's a little
bit like
what we were saying you are thinking of
hints as belonging together with what
you have explained by the word
gesture or hearing
that is so hints and gestures
according to what you indicated differ
from
signs and heifers
what's that chippers jeffers
all of which have their habitat in
metaphysics
hints and gestures belong to an entirely
different realm of reality
if you will allow this term which seems
treacherous even to myself
what you suggest confirms
a surmise i have long cherished
your phrase quote house of being unquote
must not be taken as a mere hasty image
which helps us in imagining
what we will such as house is a shelter
erected or released earlier somewhere or
another
in which being like a portable object
can be stored away
that notion proves invalid as soon as we
think of the ambiguity of quote being
unquote of which we have spoken with
that expression
i do not mean the being of beings
represented metaphysically
but the presence of being more precisely
the presence of the two-fold
being and beings but this twofold
understood in respect of its importance
for thinking them
if we heed this then your phrase can
never become a mere catchword
it already has become one
because you demand too much of today's
manner of thinking
too much quite true too much of what has
not yet ripened
human you mean ripen so that it drops
like a fruit from a tree
it seems to be that there are no such
words
a saying that would wait
for that would not be a keeping
with the nature of language
and you yourself are the last person who
would lay claim to such a saying
you do me too much honor may i return
the honor
by surmising that you are nearer to the
reality of language
than all our concepts
not i but the word for which you
are asking the word which i
now somewhat embolden may
hardly withhold from you any longer
this remark tells me that your word
still withheld
the reality of what we call language
i was prescient of you guy still
withheld
for the reality of what we call language
will bring us a surprise
such as we dare not to hope for even now
okay so
so here we are like we're a few lines
down from
like naming the withholding and then
we're just circling around and he's
talking and it still hasn't bared so
so here's so this is a this is
interesting this is this
what is it right now prior to it being
said
like we're clearly talking about it
what is this and what is that
presence for which
they're both bare you can hear them
they're bearing it to each other and
being bared from it and by it
right that's yeah
it's like the object of the speech is
becoming
attentive to the there of its
of its
of its backdrop of its of the space
of the space that has yielded to it
it's like the object of the speech is
becoming
aware of its as heidegger put it it's
authentic there
yeah this is this is this gives me
this gives me this makes my dyslexia
sing with pride right
as well it should like what in in some
sense the twofold
in some way they're presencing
the being the big b right
in some way first and keeping it in its
own nature before
the word the being i i think that's
another way of
talking about it is they're teasing out
the background
right in a kind of negative
thing it's kind of the it like negative
feel almost like a negative theological
way
right right right but but different
because
it it it still can be spoken in fact
there
it's precisely that it can be spoken
which allows for
them to withhold it but that's like in
some sense they're letting
linger a glimpse of the being of beings
right i think that's maybe
being as is heidegger talked about
before like
being not as as not as
housed by metaphysics not the
metaphysics of
being but the presence of being or the
presence of
the twofold so i think there's something
there's some kind of play
being unconcealed there absolutely
yeah absolutely all right
um okay
um j that's
over to you it's like that could be
yeah yeah that could be
that surprise however which
will strike you with the same force
with which it is holding me captive ever
since your question
needs to have the possibility of
swinging widely
i'll read that again that could be
that surprise however
will strike you with the same force
with which it is holding me
captive ever since your question
needs to have the possibility of
swinging
widely
okay very good very good
which is why you hesitate
emboldened by your in indication
that the word is a hint and not a fine
in the sense of mere signification
he asked much more a symbol than a sign
that's why dialogues that's why dialogos
which is the capacity to bear the hints
of being
is symbolic and not a is a symbolic
process
rather than a semiotic process semiotic
process in the in the very very narrow
then very narrow definition of the term
is consisting only in signs
right because it's this conversation
is about the inexpressible rather than
the expressed
yeah yes and this is a symbolic process
rather than a
and a sign oriented one
and the presence oh that's right
the inexpressed right or the
inexpression exactly
right exactly that's exactly impertinent
oh very good you still don't know what
the word is
nope hints
need the white yeah that's
uh that's my line oh i'm sorry that's
your life
hints need the widest sphere in which to
swing
where mortals go to whoa
only slowly
this is what our language calls hesitate
it is done truly when slowness rests on
shy
reverence and so i do not wish to
disturb your hesitation
by urging you on too rashly wow
wow wow hesitate it is done
slowness rest on shy reverence
oh what a line that's a great line
when slo that's like gonna drop that one
down
when slowness rests on shy reverence
yeah shy rebel shy
reverence that's probably the best
it's the best description of the
attitude that i often feel
when in some of our
dialogues especially when we do those
like this the ones with john and jordan
like horrible me you know what i mean
shy reverence is is uh that rings true
yeah and there's a hesitation and i
think i'm starting to understand
the reverence and respect of that
hesitation
right it's it's it's a transparent
to that or
one the danger right
of saying it too early right
and and that we're in the realm of
wanting um
wanting uh in some sense the unknown
to be disclosed without raping it of its
of its own right like we want the
unknown to be present without having to
make it known
and a respect and a shyness because you
can never quite
yeah because it's so much yeah it's so
much about negativity
right of humility
and yeah it's really
it's yeah
make a t-shirt on that one all right
that's right ah
that's a good idea yeah replace all of
those awful
keep calm and whatever the hell t-shirts
this this is
this yes yes
yes more helpful to me
in my attempt to say the word than you
can
know
i shall not hide from you that you are
throwing me into a state of great
agitation
especially because i you guys got blue
balls right on
process is fraught with eros
that's good that's good i shall not hide
from you that you are throwing me into a
state of great agitation
especially because all my efforts to get
an answer to my question from language
experts and linguistic scholars of
language have so far been in vain
but in order to have in order that your
reflection may swing freely
almost without your prompting let us
exchange roles
and let me be the one who gives the
answers specifically
the answer to your question about
hermeneutics
we are back then on the path which we
took
first in our dialogue
a path which a path on which we did not
get very far with an explanation
explication rather of hermeneutics i
told you stories rather
showing how i came to employ the word i
just want to put
i want to point out here so that movie
just did
right it's basically saying like all
right already
like
it's like the point in the socratic
dialogue when the the the intellectuals
but socrates you still haven't given me
the goddamn definition
yes yes and then he's he basically
he's saying his agitation basically and
then
he takes the ball and turns it back
around
i don't know there's something very
socratic about that
right oh totally yeah yeah unmistakably
unmistakably
while i in turn noted that now
you do not use it in any long use it any
longer
yeah does it use
hermenetics after i think after being
in time maybe a little bit later he
stopped using that way of describing his
work
finally i emphasize that hermeneutics
used as an adjunct board to
phenomenology
does not have its usual meaning
methodology of interpretation
but means the interpretation itself
then our dialogue yes
that's a pretty key that's a pretty key
uh
uh a pretty key hint to heidegger's
thinking eh yeah what's that one
line fill that out a little bit how so
so
like it's like saying like it does it
does not it does not have the usual
meaning
method interpretation
but means interpretation itself so it's
not the methodology of interpretation
but it's interpreted it's it's the
it's the it's the relational being yeah
yeah
okay cool that our dialogue drifted away
into the undefined
fortunately oh yes fortune
[Laughter]
even so thank you for coming back
once more to hermionetics
as i do so i would like to start from
the etymology of the word
it will show you that my use of the word
is non-arbitrary
and that is also is apt
to clarify the intention of my
experiment with phenomenology
i am all the more puzzled
that you have meanwhile drop both words
that was done not as it is often thought
in order to deny
the significance of phenomenology but in
order to abandon my own path of thinking
to namelessness
oh so abandon my own path of thinking
to namelessness so he wanted to like let
go of the name
and abandon it to okay not in the
confines of that okay
an effort with which you you will hardly
be successful
since what cannot since one cannot get
by
uh in public without rubrics
but that cannot prevent you from giving
also a
a more precise explanation of the terms
hermenetics and or hermeneutics
and hermeneutic which you have meanwhile
abandoned
i shall be glad to try because the
explanation may
issue in a discussion
in the sense in which the lecture on
trackle pope and the trackles poetry
understanding discussion
exactly in that sense the expression
hermeneutic derives from the greek verb
hermeneuen
that verb is related to the noun
hermeneus
which is referable to the name of the
god hermes by a playful thinking that is
more compelling
than the rigor of science hermes
is the divine messenger he brings us the
message of destiny
hermeneuen is that exposition which
brings tidings because it can listen
to a message such exposition becomes an
interpretation of what has been said
earlier by the poets who according to
socrates in plato's ion
hermeneus icinton theon
are interpreters of the gods
well let's let that sit for a second
totally
and i remember like hermes was the god
the messenger god
and he was the wings on his feet even
like
full apollo right he was like the god
clarity you know
um and so but he's also
not considered totally a god or totally
a human he's in this in-between world
right yeah such it's it's usually
that's why interpretation right language
um
it is very much associated with message
because it's like
the word right you can't find the word
in the shape of the letter
right it's like you don't even know
quite when you read a word
where does it where is the word is it in
the shape right is it in the
mind is it is it you saying it or is it
the author saying it
all these things start to fall apart
without definition and that's
that's the space of mercury of
hermionetic and that's why it's
it's involved with trickery because it
can
you know tricksters can always undo
authority they're the ones that like
the fool is the one person that can undo
the king when it gets too grandiose
right right right
and and what's interesting about this
too is
now i i think i heard this from hillman
i i may have misheard it because i
haven't been able to find it i haven't
been able to read it
but my understanding is actually in some
of the in some of the stories hermes was
married to i believe hestia
which is which is fascinating because
hestia
is the i think the goddess domesticity
right and i think hilleman used to use
this um
yeah yeah for like the flying boy
because you know he would talk a lot a
lot about inflation
and he said hermetic inflation was in a
certain sense where
hermes divorces domesticity and becomes
icarus right and flies through the sun
and
you have this you know these manic you
get
too too high in the air and then you die
and you fall back down or you
stick your finger in a light pocket and
he's because he said
because hermes is supposed to be wedded
to hestia which is the god
goddess of domesticity of you know of a
certain kind of
order of like repetition of
sameness of things have their place that
in that nurturing
kind of homelessness so there's a
marriage and attention there that's
that on some level this whole
conversation has been about that
tension right between the apparent and
the non-apparent the
concealment and intentional withholding
oh lots of
it's been a total hermetic
that's great what a rich connection
you've just drawn yeah
and they've been very yeah she's been
very i'm gonna i'm gonna chase after
that a little bit
uh i'd like to find out i'd like to find
out more about the about the myth
yeah i'm not familiar i'm not familiar
with it at all that at least that
particular
yeah the the hermit
that coupling i'm pretty sure i heard
that in
it in hillman because i was reading
hillman a lot at that time
i haven't read him in a while i should
read him again just to
see if i still like him or what he
sounds like now
anything more you want to say about this
one no i think you
i think you said it and beautifully and
he's saying so he's also
he's also talking about the plate so and
also you know and i think he's also
he's pointing out in scholasticism
right in the middle ages right after
once aristotle got misinterpreted and
you know all that stuff about substance
and um
i think he's he's he's saying like her
like her menetics got really kind of dry
maybe even abstract and scholarly in a
certain sense and so he's kind of going
back to the
arkey of it and wanting to release the
playfulness
and the prime primordiality of it yeah
release the fumes back into the air yes
exactly
and that right baby the fumes back in
the air
she said i've i've eaten something here
lately
and she's been um
see we keep talking about listening for
the logos we should just be smelling for
it
yes exactly and listen and listening to
brienne
i don't recommend smelling for it
hi brianne
all right i think i'm gonna go next
i'm very fond of this short platonic
dialogue
in the passage you have in mind socrates
carries the affinities
even further by summarizing
that the rapides are those who
bear the tidings of the poet's word
all this makes it clear that
hermeneutics means not just the
interpretation
but even before it the bearing of the
message and tidings
okay there's that word again the bearing
of the message the bearing of the
message and tidings
the hearing of the messages okay
why well i like that the way that's
phrased incidentally
you know the bearing i mean the the
bearing can be understood
one of a couple of different ways but
one of the ways it can be understood it
is verbally
right the bearing that the hermeneutics
the definition of hermeneutics
um that he's giving here is one that is
verbalized it's it's motioning it's
inaction
right it's an active definition rather
than a passive one and i think that's
important
yeah totally
why do you stress this original sense of
hermeticism
okay cool i think so i think so um
because it was this original sense which
prompted me to use it in defining the
phenomenological thinking that opened
the way to being in time for me
what mattered then and still does is to
bring up the being of beings
though no longer in the manner of
metaphysics but such that being itself
will shine out
being itself that is to say the presence
of present beings
the twofold of the two in virtue of
their simple
oneness this is what makes its claim on
man
calling him to its essential being
i just want to pause with that one for a
second
so can you call me okay
this last sentence of that this is what
makes its claim on man
calling him to his essential being
can you fill that one out for me
well
to trace back to the previous sentence
such that being itself will shine out
being itself that is to say the presence
of present beings the twofold of the two
in virtue of their simple one
so what makes what this makes me think
of is
you know we talk about this this geistly
entity
that emerges in the eye of our pair
right that stands
in the phrase that describes the
relation of the eye thou
dynamism it's psychodynamism and its
dialogic
structure and so what happens there
is that that emergent entity is
precisely what
calls the attention of the soul right it
calls the
it calls the primordial memory of man
and the essential being that is
described and articulated
in that primordial memory now that's
and i'm not giving a definition of that
but i'm just just to say what it what
what it draws from me what it what i
what comes to my mind when i
read that the last couple of sentences
is that emergent that emergent
collective entity that generates
the acoustic attunement to the logos
that we so often describe
and what what it means to make its claim
on man
because it it draws it draws the
identity
of any participant who is witness
to who bears wit i think garusan's
bearing witness to epiphany right
who bears witness to its emergence it's
epiphanic emergence
it draws the identity of those
participants
because it is it is constitutive
of those identities and so making its
claim on man to me
in some ways is making its claim on the
identity
of logos yes but
from from the beings to its being
yes yes
nice calling them back calling logos
back to logos
and in a sense
glad i asked thank you
when i asked
i'm gonna have to listen to your i'm
absolutely i'm absolutely listening to
the recording of that one
as as am i as am i yeah yeah this is a
good one
yeah this is the so man
then realizes his nature as man
by corresponding to the call of the
twofold
and bears witness to it in its message
okay so this is okay this is
that okay actually i was trying to
describe this the other day
of where you know i was i was talking to
somebody
and it you know it was kind of an
unusual conversation or something and
they were
trying to get into my head somehow or i
was trying to describe it and it and i
and i it got present to like
at some point in
at some point in my life
all all i could say is all i could think
about is this stuff
like like all i can think about is
is the stuff like that that we're
reading about like it just became
at some point it just became constant
always there
always a question always more than i had
i think i had
actually ever realized it and so when i
hear this i'm like
god that's there's something about that
just rings so true
it's like so at some level at some level
man then realizes his nature
so we could say on some level i'm
realizing
my nature guy then realizes his nature
as guy by corresponding to the call of
the twofold
and guy bears witness to it in its
message
oh that's a that's a that's a very
clever that's a very clever clever
substitution you just made
yeah does that doesn't that actually
bring it out that much more
yeah yeah it kind of does but that
actually describes it it's like
bear witness to it in its message
that's exactly the thing that
the door that opened and it's like
it's like a possession or
something like that
so anyways i i'm just i i think i got
i got a little bit more of man in that
moment
got a little bit more of man yep
accordingly what prevails in and bears
up the relation of human nature to the
twofold is language
language defines the hermeneutic
relation
thus now we're on the way to language
it's about time um thus
when i ask you about hermenetics and
when you ask
me what our word is for what you call
language
we ask each other the same and the same
is capitalized
clearly perhaps this is where we're
coming back to that stream between
yeah maybe this is we're circling back
here
clearly and that is why we may
confidently entrust ourselves to the
hidden
drift of our dialogue
hidden drift another another good turn
of phrase
it's like a coffee cup right there
coming up with all kinds of ways to
merchandise this and
monetize this endeavor of ours you're
american right
um
i'm not i'm not i'm not disapproving yes
um as long as we remain in choirs
oh well there go there goes my whole
business model right there okay that was
weird many requires
you do not mean that we are pumping each
other out of
curiosity but
but but rather that we go
we go right on releasing into the open
whatever might be said
sorry about that my uh my my
13 year old brain is uh having a great
great time with that
[Laughter]
i don't i don't necessarily think that
the connotation's unintended though
right um
okay that could all too easily give the
impression that everything we say
drifts away non-committally
we can encounter the impression
by paying heed to the doctrine of past
thinkers
and always let them to take
part in our dialogue what i have just
said
is something i learned from you
what you learned there has been much
learned in turn
by listening to the thinkers thinking
each man is in each instance in dialogue
with his four bears
and perhaps even more and more sorry
and perhaps even more and in a more
hidden manner with those who will come
after him
wow so i did i wanna i wanna i just
wanna pause on this
one right here what what he says is
this is a this is subtle but i think
this may be
um what you learned there
has been learned in turn by listening
to thinkers thinking
right he didn't say listeners lis listen
to
um thinkers think
listen to thinkers he said
thinkers thinking what's
i mean heidegger never writes a
word that isn't
like saturated in every way meaningful
right um i don't know if you notice he's
not one
one for small talk it seems
and then he says i wanna get that for a
second so
what you learned there has been has been
learned
so he's actually talking about
historicity right the history
yes exactly right
historicization of thinking so in some
sense
in some sense is thinking
is you're doing that when you start to
notice
it's not even it's it's probably not
even when you just like explicitly quote
kant or talk explicitly talk about what
they thought
it's when thought
catches sight of
it's starting from a starting perhaps
starting from a thought
that was originally thought by another
thinker that made that your thought
possible it's like catching a whiff of
that
so in a certain sense to think to to
listen to a thinker's thinking
right is
as much as to listen to your own
thinking
right um
which is really an interesting thing
about like and also listen and thinking
because it's
listening and thinking are so tied to
each other like
because that's why is as i'm talking if
you were to have a thought
you'd have to come back after that
thought
and realize that you weren't listening
to me there's like you can't
and you can't think and
listen at the same time they're like the
same thing
right that's right so in some sense
and then listening
i guess it's also true with thinking
it's kind of like when you say
you know if you were to if i were to ask
you how teach me how to think
right like
you would instantly realize that
you you don't you don't you know how
you don't know how you think you'd
probably say well i just think
you can't like there's a um
there's an implicit knowing right in
which
you think you can't go well first move
this neuron and then
this foot and right you
just think right um
and i think therefore how do you learn
to think
philosophically how do you learn to
listen
well we say about listening because it's
one of the things i've noticed in
in training people to circle which is a
lot about listening and what
what you got to realize is you can't
teach people how to listen
what you can do is you can have them
maybe have them notice that they don't
listen
yes yes yes
moment that they hear
themselves not listening right yes the
moment listening has already begun
so there's just something about that
there's something there right
i can't that's a great insight guy and
it and it
brings us it brings us right back to
socrates you can't
teach people how to listen you can only
teach them to notice when they're not
listening
yes yes
in fact it's yeah i think that's the
whole thing and i think that's the whole
thing with
the history of being or the history of
the understanding of being
right is precisely this is what
heidegger talks about it like is
the history of the understanding of pain
is
the forgetfulness of itself being a
history of the understanding of being it
is a
it is a forgetfulness of its original
thought
with the pre-socratic where you're like
you know the aussia right oh there's
that which all of this partakes and is
of in some way and
the very beginnings of that right and
it's funny to think about it
if they if if that original
philosophical thinking
right which was the first trying to
abstract the sense that
there may be all of the individual
beings that it may be
somehow connected to being as such that
had not been thought before
if that hadn't have happened there
wouldn't be
this computer there wouldn't be any of
the sciences
there wouldn't have been it's it's
it's asked like it's astonishing
right to what degree we sit
and dwell and are indwelled by and
saturated
with what began then right
and it's just it's stunning but it's
also
the beginning this is one of the things
i was trying to kind of tease out in my
paper
is that sense of it's
it's the very it's very what that
allowed the open
i think it really happened right like
the speaking of the logos right um
and par permitted these right but when
the openness and the possibility of the
logos being heard as
logos right um
that possibility of that he being able
to hear
also right was the same openness that
afforded
the mistakenness of of
listening to to beings versus being
the very openness that afforded right
afforded the hearing of being right is
the same openness that afforded the
the deafening of it yeah
so this it's interesting so to think
about this so cut like
this is why they're taking such great
care here they're exemplifying such a
great
care to be
aware of of essentially self-deception
right of let's make sure we're listening
like they're basically saying let's
let's make sure that we're listening
um to what we're saying here and
listening to what we're not saying here
and i think there's an awareness
of the trickery of this or hermes
so yeah a lot of that stuff's kind of
everything yeah including the thing i
didn't say
always that's what i meant
well said and well not said yeah thank
you
thank you well
well not paraphrased
[Laughter]
it needed no paraphrase no paraphrasal
all right all right where are we here
um okay so i'll just read that part
again what you learned there
has been learned in turn by listening to
the
thinkers thinking
each man is in each instant in dialogue
with his forebears
and perhaps even more and
in a more hidden manner those who will
come
after him
in a deeper sense this historical nature
of every thinking dialogue is not
however in need
of all those enterprises which in the
matter of historiography
report things from the past about the
thinkers and what they have thought
certainly not
but for us today it may become a
pressing need
to prepare such conversations
by interpreting properly what
earlier thinkers have said
something that could easily degenerate
into mere
busy work this
is a danger we save off as long
as we ourselves make an effort to
think in dialogue
and as you say in your language
weigh each word
instead of thought i said a thought here
i want to point out
there's also something here that
exemplifies this i've been listening to
this guy on youtube who's a
he's a phd brilliant apparently has an
iq of like
195 or something but he's a narcissist a
pathological narcissist who's a phd
psychologist
he he puts out like sometimes two videos
a day
these long intensive descriptions
of psychopathology i'll give you a link
to him he's um
i think he's romanian or something like
that he's got he's got a kind of an
eastern accent
does he identify does he identify
himself as a narcissist
yeah he talks from with inside of it but
he's also a scholar and
it's it's fascinating well that's
interesting
right but so i've been just he's really
entertaining to listen to so i've just
been listening to him so it has me
thinking a lot about narcissism
and this sense of like how narcissism
has that quality of
of where you know psychologically
speaking it's
like where there's a there's a um a
depravity of self
right such that you were constantly
needing
um you only you only
know that you are via inference and so
in a pathological sense of the word
you're co
like if you're completely corrupted
right i.e you're completely
missing yourself any authentic self all
you have
are reifications from outside right
and so everything is about that
reification
and in some sense this dialogue right is
almost
it in some sense what it's requiring you
to be is almost the opposite of a
narcissist
right like everything is about like okay
let's withhold this let's not say this
right there's a there's a real it's
interesting to i think i want to kind of
like bring that just
into the into the fold of
especially when we think about dialogues
as
one of the ways in which
it can be a symbol of the enactment
of self-transformation right in
self-development
right and so what kinds of
cells right are having these
conversations
right and i think that's what i'm
basically pointing to here is i think
they are definitely selves that that
aren't
needing their selfhood
um to be reflected because they
it requires so much propose right so
much
not being said not being hurt kind of
it's a it's a
it's a non-narcissism in a very very
deep way
yeah it's like it requires cells that
are not things
yeah there you go
well said yeah yeah
okay that's this is fascinating i wanna
i wanna i wanna
i wanna watch some of this uh can you
send me something
of what you're watching okay
yeah careful though man he's
one of the things i think i've noticed
about when you have
psychology that um really doesn't have
much of a sense of like
um like ontology right an epistemology
in that you can pathologize
everything right yes yes yes oh
yeah
be careful just listening to it but
pretty soon like everyone's
you know a borderline with a latent
narcissism
my entire world is just going to
suddenly be rife with sick
sick and demented people yeah
all right i knew that already so that's
fine yeah absolutely yes
okay um where are we it seems
okay i think i was the last one
we we you and i just surreptitiously
switched
roles in the last step we did that's
okay let's go with it
okay good so now um
now you're you're i and i'm j okay good
um so i just said uh and as you say in
your language wait each word
but above all examine whether each word
in each case
is given it's full most often
hidden weight
it seems to me that we are following
this unwritten
prescription although i must confess i
am a very clumsy questioner
all of us remain clumsy questioners
despite much care we still keep
overlooking essentials
even here in this dialogue
which led us to discuss hermenetics and
the reality of language
for the moment i failed to see in what
way we were careless in our use of words
that is something we often notice only
quite late
because the fault lies not so much in
ourselves
as in the fact that language is more
powerful than
we and therefore weightier
what sense
to illustrate by what we were just
talking of
you said that language is the
fundamental trait in human nature's
hermeneutic relation to the twofold of
present and pre
okay let me take that called again you
said that language is the fundamental
trait in human nature's hermenetic
relation
of the twofold of presence and present
beings
to that remark i had once intended to
make a few observations
but i shall do so only after you have
shown just what we have failed to think
of
in that context
i mean the word relation quote unquote
we think of it in the sense of a
relationship
what we know in that we
can identify in i'm sorry let me start
that again
i mean the word relation we
think of it in the sense of a
relationship
what we know in that way we can identify
in an empty
in an empty formal sense and employ
like a mathematical notion think of the
procedure of logistics
but in the phrase quote
man stands in her munitical relation to
the twofold
unquote we may hear the word relation
also in a wholly different way
in fact we must if we give
thought to what was said presumably
we must and can do so not right away
but in good time after a long reflection
then it will do no harm if for the time
being
we understand relation in the customary
sense of relationship
do you do are you getting this
difference
relational relationship is that
well i'm not sure yet but
well let's think of it i mean we we
often talk about and we what this is one
of the central insights that you've
you've recently um you've recently
formalized right in the chapter that you
just wrote for the coming anthology that
you know let's think of it not as
relation but think of it as
maybe in a sense of sociality you talk
about the fact that the
the sociality between beings
is merely i don't want to put words in
your mouth but my
my understanding of your point is that
is that you're saying that the sociality
between persons
analogizes the sociality of the person
to the authors
and they are not the same they
they should not be mistaken for an
identity relation
but the socialization
of the relationship between persons
intersectingly
interpersonally avails
episteme of the relation
between the individual and
being yes and so i'm
thinking of this line very much in that
same spirit that
relationship relationship in its
concrete boundaries in its in its
definitional
familiarization it's familiarity i
should say
is a way of analogizing
it's a way of let me put maybe i'll put
in more hydrogen terms
it's the relationship between beings is
a way of thinking toward
the relation with being right and
the two forms of relation should not be
mistaken as identical but one serves as
a proxy for the other
and so for the purpose of this
conversation it'll do
yes okay that's what i take it to mean
thank you
thank you that's what i take i'm not
sure if that's it but that's
my sense of it at least so far nope you
didn't put any words in my mouth
excellent thank you
then oh no let i'm taking over again
oh okay sorry um uh okay
true oh we're switching back look at
that
true but it is adequate from the start
you're one above it then i'm one above
it
start with then it will do you know okay
sorry then it will do no harm
if for the time being we understand
relation and the customary sense of
relationship
true but it is inadequate from the start
assuming that the word relation is to
become
a mainstay of our statement
we say correlation
quote unquote also when talking about
the supply and demand of commodities
if man is in a hermeneutical relation
however that means that he is precisely
not a commodity but the word relation
does want to say that man in his very
being
is in demand is needed
that he as the being he is
belongs within a needfulness
which claims him wow
the word relation does not want to say
that man and his very being is
in demand is needed that he is the being
he is belongs within a needfulness which
claims
and the needfulness that claims them is
that's something that's that analogous
that's the that's the world
right
claiming him right that's the being it's
the yeah
it's the original being that he's
thinking after that goes
before him totally
but the word relation does not
does want to say that man in his very
being
is in demand okay is in demand
and his very being is in demand okay so
it's it's not like i'm a being that then
is in demand
that i be i am already always
in demand
i'm needed in that same way
that he that i as the being
i am belongs within
and i belong within
a needfulness which claims him
wow okay
it's it's a tough one to parse very
tough one to parse
in what sense
well glad you asked over to you
well of course hermeneutically
that is decision with respect to
bringing tidings
with respect to preserving a message
okay hermeneutically that is to say
with respect to bringing tidings
with respect to preserving
a message preserve so let's think of
preserving the message
in the same context as bearing the
speech
before its speech right yeah preserving
yeah and that kind of historical sense
right in a very deep way yeah okay
man stands in relation when says
sorry man stands in relation then says
the same as
man is really as men when needed and
used by
what calls on man to preserve the
twofold
which as far as i can see cannot be
explained in terms of presence
nor in terms of present beings nor in
terms
of the relation of the two
because it is only the twofold itself
which unfolds the clarity
that is the clearing
in which present beings as such
and presence can be discerned by man
i want to read that again because
because it is only the two-fold being
and beings
itself that itself
being and beings which unfolds so being
beings unfolds the clarity
that is the clearing in which
present beings so
beings as such
and presence can be discerned by man
by man who by nature stands in relation
to
that is being used by the twofold
ah so basically we're being we're just
in
constantly just being used and raped by
the twofold
ding oh here we go okay that's it ah
that was easy
[Laughter]
this is also why you no longer say
relation to the people for the twofold
is not an object of mental
representation
but is the sway of the usage
this is this is only by this is
also why we may no longer say
relation to the twofold
or the twofold is not an object of
mental representation
but is the sway of usage
which we never experience directly
however as long as we think of the
twofold only as
the difference which becomes apparent
in a comparison that tries to contrast
present
beings and their presence i'm going to
read that again
which we never so which and the which is
um the twofold so that
twofold is not an object of metro
representation but is the sway of usage
the sway of usage
which we never experience directly
however as long as we think of the
twofold only as the difference
which becomes apparent in a comparison
that tries to contrast
present beings and their presence
anything you want to highlight on that
now
i don't think so i'm still just
digesting it
by the way have they said it yet
no
[Laughter]
they still haven't said it okay
i am surprised that you see so clearly
me too
when i can follow you in the dialogue i
succeed
left alone i am helpless for even the
manner
in which you employ the words relation
and use
we're not alone the
japanese guy is with us um
when he can follow or
better the manner in which i use
them italics use
is strange enough
i don't deny it but it seems to me
that in the field in which we are moving
we reach those things which we are
originally
familiar precisely if we do
not shun passing through things
strangely
strange to us that's such that same word
in what sense do you understand
original originally familiar
you do not mean what we know first do
you
no but that the f that
before all else has been entrusted
to our nature and becomes known
only at the last
and that is what you're thinking pursues
yeah what you're thinking what
heidegger's thinking pursues here
is um what before all else has been
entrusted
to our nature twofold
the thing that hasn't been said yet the
bearing
all that right and becomes known
only in the last
i'm just thinking about
something there's a link here okay oh
most certainly most certainly yeah
okay and then i say only that
but in this way that in it
there is a the there is veal
veiled all that is worthy of thought as
such
and as a whole
and in that thinking you pay no heed to
the current ideas of your fellows
it seems that way of course but in truth
every thinking step om
step only serves the effort to help
man in his thinking to find the path of
his essential
being hence
your reflection on language
on language in its relation to the
nature of being
capital b that is to say
to the to the sway of the twofold
but if language is the basic trait in
hermeneutically defined usage
then you experience the reality of
language from the start
differently from the way one does in
metaphysical thinking
this is what i had intended to point out
earlier
but what for not for the sake of
contrasting something new with a
conventional
but to remind us that our dialogue
speaks historically precisely in its
attempt to reflect on the nature of
language
it speaks out of the thinking respect
of the past and this
yes and this
is just what was to be noted in the
little of the lecture series the copy of
which was frequently discussed in the
20s
among us japanese i must be
frank and tell you that here you are
mistaken
the lecture series quote expression
and appearance unquote or was not
the title expression and meaning
was still rather um controversial
even though it remained informed by what
we now
call the historic character of thinking
dialogue
title then was to point up a contrast
in any event i was concerned
to bring into view that which is wholly
different
of which however i had only
an obscure if not confused intimation
such youthful capers
easily lead to do injustice
the word expression in the title is the
name
for what you opposed for your gaze into
the lan
for your gaze into the nature of
language does not fasten upon the
phonetics of the written forms of the
words
which are generally conceived to
constitute the expressive nature of
language
the name expression is here understood
in the narrow sense of sensuous
appearance yet even where our attention
is focused on the content of meaning
in the phonetic and written formulations
even there language is still conceived
as
expressive in character
how so speech i understood in the
fullness of its meaning
transcends and does so always the
physical
sensible side of phonetics language is a
sense that is sounded and written
is in itself super sensuous something
that constantly transcends the merely
sensible
so understood language is in itself
metaphysical i agree with everything you
propose but language makes its
appearance
in this metaphysical nature only
insofar as it is before
hand understood to be expression
expression does not mean here
only the enunciated sounds of speech
and the printed sign of writing
expression is simultaneously
utterance okay so just i just want to
summarize a little bit what they're
talking about so he's they're basically
making the point
they're talking about essentially
you can't reduce language down or the
dialectic is you can't reduce language
down to the to its
um material aspects to the sound of the
voice
or the shape of the letter or the
sentence structure always transcends
and he's saying yes and
this last part expression does not mean
hear
only the enunciated sounds of speech in
the predecessor but
expression is oh no there's i agree with
that proposed i agree with what i just
summarized there
and then he's making this point though i
want to make sure
that i make sure and more deeply not
understand it
um but language makes its appearance
in this in this metaphysical nature
only insofar as
it as it is beforehand understood
to be expression okay so
what he's saying is all the forms of
language
um are there by virtue of which
an already um
understanding of those things
being expressive that's the base that's
the
that's the intelligibles because we hear
them as
expressives we we prehend them
as expressives okay
we can apprehend them yeah exactly he
says
expression is simultaneously utterance
that's probably going to be important
bearings and
[Music]
utterance refers to its inwardness
of what pertains to the soul
you want to give that a second seems
like one that you would
tickle you
it does i'm going to let it stand though
but it does
look i just want to appreciate the
the leading as it stands um
in the days of the of that in the days
of that lecture everyone was talking
about experience
even within phenomenology
a famous book by delphi has the title
experience and poetry
to experience in this sense always means
to refer
back to
for life and lived experience back to
the i
experience is the name
for the referral of the objective
back to the subject the much
discussed i thou experience
two belongs within the metaphysical
sphere of subjectivity
and this sphere of subjectivity and of
the expression that belongs to
it is what you left behind when you
entered into the hermenetic relation
of the twofold at least i tried
the guiding notion which under the
name's
expression experience and consciousness
determine modern thinking were to be
put in question with respect to the
decisive
role they
but then i no longer understand how you
could choose the title
expression and appearance it was
intended was it not to announce a
contrast
expression is the utterance of something
internal and refers to the subjective
appearance on the contrary names the
objective if i may hear recall const
usage
according to which appearances of the
objects the objects of experience
by giving your lecture a title you did
commit yourself to the subject object
relation
in a certain respect your objective is
justified
if only for the reason that much had
to remain unclear in those lectures
nobody can in just one single leap
take um distance from the predominant
circle of ideas especially not
if he is dealing with the well worn
tracks of traditional thinking
tracks that fade into realms where they
they can hardly be seen besides
taking such distance from all tradition
is
tempered by the very fact that the
seeming
subversive will tries above all
to recover the things of the past in a
more originary form
it is on purpose that the first page
of being in time speaks of
raising again a question
what is meant is not the monotonous
trotting out of something that is always
the same
but to fetch
to gather in to bring together
what is concealed within the old
hmm
our teachers and my friends in japan
i've always understood your efforts in
that sense
professor tanabe often came back to a
question you once put to him
why it was that we japanese did not call
back
to mind the venerable beginnings of your
own thinking
instead of chasing ever more greedily
after the latest news in european
philosophy
as a matter of fact we still do today we
do so
still today it is not easy
to go counter to this tendency
such procedures in good time
are smothered by their own sterility
but what requires our contribution
is a different matter which would be
to give to the trails that direct
thinking
back to the region of its source
that's a good line to give heat to the
trails the direct thinking
into the region of its source
that line right there i think is in a
way that i didn't understand at the time
um is how
heidegg reading heidegger precisely
because it does that on so many
it's even doing that now way
where your habits is it's like it has
you're thinking about something that you
don't know yet
yes but then as you go along you realize
that he's
explicating the very basis upon which
is um your thinking in some sense
from and elucidating so it's like yeah
it's this step forward
that has you end up back prior
to right
doing that over and over and over and
over and over again like
and then and then circling back and
forth heidegger and then circling
heidegger and then circling
there was that i started to i think i
started to
notice that that's precisely how insight
happens
right yes yes
that's right that's right and that's the
way that's that's the dialectic
yeah yeah
yeah that's that's an important
punctuation mark
yeah really important that's a really
important punctuation mark
yeah really important to give heat to
the trails the direct thinking back
to the region of its source yeah
so it's like no it takes it so he didn't
just go back give heed to the tracks
which means that it's there the tracks
are present
but what i think he's saying if he
to the tracks and he's saying they they
fade
in other words they stop occurring
as well i think how they occur is just
what looks like given facts right
the world just you just i mean i think
everybody kind of wakes up in the
morning and they the alarm clock goes
off they open their eyes
and they think they're just instantly
taking in data
right just seeing what's out there um
so you give heed in some sense
to those historical tracks it's just
somehow
over here yeah it's like to
to overhear your participation in the
matter
a little bit down to the left
right yeah
it's
i'm getting this i'm getting this image
of um
lost it it's okay
i heard it had it
lost it thought i had it again lost it
again exactly and then i realized it
wasn't
it wasn't it wasn't worth trying to
fabricate exactly
and you you were able to do it without
having to heat
yeah shall we go on are we are we
i think i think i'm going to have to
dash my friend totally
but let's let's pick this up soon
because i think we've got some steam
and i will make a note actually of what
page we're on so we don't have to chase
it
back and i'll even fold my page
this is really great this is a joy
as it always is thank you it's gonna be
lingering
for a while yeah for me too
me too this is a great text this was an
inspired idea
she says she says you're wonderful yeah
you guys are uh
enjoy listening she's very
you're very kind brianne you're very
very kind that's
that's just this is a joy it's pure joy
it's just it's easy
yes it's just
that even more emphatically than she
says how much she
she hates my farts oh god
and on that note
all right man see you later bye brienne
bye